Othmane Rifki, Ph.D.

□ +1-773-888-3269 ✓ othrif@gmail.com 🏕 https://othrif.github.io 🗘 /othrif Permanent US Resident

Summary _____

Data scientist with 7 years experience and in-depth understanding of analytic methods and their implementations. Performed statistical analysis of large datasets processed with large-scale distributed computing systems using C/C++ and Python.

Part of a 3000+ person collaboration searching for rare signals among large backgrounds in high energy proton-proton collisions at the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) Long involvement in codebase of more than 10 million lines of C++ and almost as many lines of Python Expert in petabyte data reduction (ATLAS 10 PB/year), world-wide grid computing, and data visualization Lead analysis groups as "Editor" in two searches for signals of supersymmetry and other exotic decays, managed a team of 5-6 analysts, eventually wrote the research paper, and defended its approval—a period of about a year

- 2+ years of machine learning using pandas, scikit-learn, TensorFlow, OpenCV

Skills

- ② Languages: Analyzed and visualized high-value datasets with software packages developed in multiple languages
 - Core languages: Python, C/C++/STL (10+ years)
 - Data science software: matplotlib, numpy, scipy, scikit-learn, pandas, jupyter, Keras, TensorFlow, OpenCV, docker
 - General software: Linux, bash, git, svn, QT, Matlab, Mathematica
- **O** Leadership: Led several scientific groups to achieve time-critical targets
 - Managed teams of 5-20 researchers leading to several peer-reviewed journal publications
 - Supervised PhD and Master students with successful thesis defenses
 - · Organized and chaired weekly meetings and delegated tasks with emphasis on individual strengths
- **O** Communication: Excelled in written and verbal communication skills
 - Fluent in English, French, Arabic with basic skills in German
 - Presented the latest scientific advancements at notable international conferences with 500+ attendees
 - Summarized research and data analysis to non-technical audiences at various outreach activities (example)

Publication:

• Published 15 scientific papers in peer-reviewed particle physics and instrumentation journals (complete list)

Experience ____

<u>Deutsches Elektronen-Synchrotron (DESY)</u>

Post-Doctoral Research Fellow

Hamburg, Germany Sep 2017 - Present

Sep 2017 Tresent

- Performed likelihood-based statistical analyses on a petabyte-scale dataset, using predictive modeling algorithms
- Automated pick-and-place assembly with robotics and advanced optics to achieve micron level precision
- Achieved high accuracy pattern matching using computer vision algorithms in challenging conditions
- Administered a laboratory budget of **300k Euros** coordinating a team of scientists, engineers, and suppliers

European Organization for Nuclear Research (CERN))

Doctoral Researcher

Geneva, Switzerland Jul 2015 - Aug 2017

- Designed real-time data processing algorithms with strict real-time performance to process 160 gigabytes/second
- Supervised a team of 10 scientists to ensure high-quality data recorded by the ATLAS detector at CERN

Argonne National Laboratory (ANL)

Research Fellow

Lemont, IL, United States
May 2014 - Jun 2015

Won a \$30k US level Analysis Support Center fellowship awarded to 2 students a year to work with ANL scientists

• Simulated complex particles production and interaction using IBM Mira, one of the world's fastest supercomputers

Education

- **Our University of Oklahoma** Ph.D. in High Energy Physics
- **⊘ Drexel University** *B.Sc. in Physics with High Honors*

Norman, OK, United States
Philadelphia, PA, United States

Activities

- **⊘** Triathlon: Competing in the Hamburg Landesliga in the 2018 and 2019 seasons
- **O Diving:** CMAS 3 star diver with TDI advanced nitrox certification